<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="cinnamon-desktop">
    <title>Introduction to the Desktop</title>

    <para>The <wordasword>desktop</wordasword> is the component of the operating system which is responsible for the elements that appear on the desktop: The <wordasword>Panel</wordasword>, the <wordasword>Wallpaper</wordasword>, the <wordasword>Control Center</wordasword>, the menus... etc.</para>
    <para>The Cinnamon Edition of Linux Mint uses the Cinnamon desktop which is both intuitive and powerful.</para>

    <sect1>
        <title>The Menu</title>

        <para>In Cinnamon, almost everything is accessible from the 'Menu'. To open it, click on <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> at the bottom-left of your screen, or press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Super_L</keycap></keycombo> (Super_L is the left Windows key on your keyboard).</para>

        <figure id="cinnamon-desktop-menu-figure">
            <title>The Cinnamon Menu</title>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/desktops/cinnamon/places-menu.png" format="PNG" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>The menu is used to launch applications, to access the system settings, and to reach common places and open recent files.</para>            
    </sect1>
        
    <sect1>
        <title>Places</title>
        <para>In Linux Mint, all your personal data is stored in your <wordasword>Home</wordasword> directory.</para>
        <para>As well as your files, this directory also contains pre-defined sub-directories such as <wordasword>Documents</wordasword>, <wordasword>Music</wordasword>, <wordasword>Videos</wordasword>...etc which you can use to better organize your files.</para>
        <para>Other important places are your <wordasword>Desktop</wordasword> folder (which containsn the files visible on your desktop), the filesystem (which contains all system files and directories), removable devices connected to the computer, the network and bookmarks (you can bookmark any directory to gain quick-access to it).</para>
        <para>To quickly access one of these places, perform one of the following actions:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Click on <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> and select <guisubmenu>Places</guisubmenu></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Launch <wordasword>Nemo</wordasword>, the Cinnamon file manager, by clicking on <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> and selecting <guimenuitem>Files</guimenuitem>. Then, within Nemo, you can access common places by clicking on them in the sidebar, on the left of the window.</para></listitem>        
        </itemizedlist>        

        <figure id="cinnamon-desktop-nemo-figure">
            <title>Nemo, the file manager, listing the content of the Home directory and providing quick-access to common places from the left sidebar.</title>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/desktops/cinnamon/nemo.png" format="PNG" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
        </figure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>System Settings</title>
        
        <para>To launch the system settings, click on <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> and select <guimenuitem>System Settings</guimenuitem>.</para>

        <figure id="cinnamon-desktop-settings-figure">
            <title>System Settings</title>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/desktops/cinnamon/systemsettings.png" format="PNG" width="100%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
        </figure>        
    </sect1>
    
</chapter>
